[{"question":"A secondary amine is","a":"(a) acompound with twocabon atomandan N, group","b":"(b) a compound containing two-NH, groups.","c":"(c) a compound in which hydrogens of NII, have been replaced by two alkyl groups","d":"(d) a compound with an-NII, group on Carbon atom in number two position","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Which of the following is not characteristic of amines?","a":"(a) They smell like ammenia","b":"(b) They are inflammable in air","c":"(c) They show the property of hydrogen bonding","d":"(d) They are amphotericin nature.","hint":"Amines are basic in nature.","correct":"d"},{"question":"Substitution of one alkyl group by replacing hydrogen of  Which of the following alkyl halides is best suited for this  primary annes","a":"(a)increases the base strength","b":"(b)Decreases the the base straigh","c":"(c) remains the same ","d":"(D) None of the above","hint":"Secondary amine is more basic than primary amine","correct":"a"},{"question":"Primary amines can be distinguished from secondary and  tertiary amines by reacting with","a":"(a) Chloroform And alcoholic kOH","b":"(B) Methyl indide","c":"(c) ChloroForm alone ","d":"(d)zinc dust","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"When bromination of aniline is carried out by protecting NIL The product is","a":"(a) o-bromoaniline","b":"(b) 2,4,6 tribooniline","c":"(c) p-Bromoaniline ","d":"(d) mixture of- oandp-bromoanilines","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"When bromination of aniline is carried out by protecting NIL The product is","a":"(a) o-bromoaniline","b":"(b) 2,4,6 tribooniline","c":"(c) p-Bromoaniline ","d":"(d) mixture of- oandp-bromoanilines","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Aniline and other arylamines are usually colourless but  gt coloured on storage due to","a":"(a) hydrolysis","b":"(b) dehydration","c":"(c) reduction","d":"(d) atmospheric oxidation","hint":"Antine and other aryl amines reacts with air and Get oxidised ","correct":"d"},{"question":"Arrange the following in increasing onder of their Basic strength p-nitriline (1), nitamline (2),2,4,6-transthylaniline(7):3-methylaniline (4)","a":"(a) 1,3,2,4","b":"(b) 2,3,4,1","c":"(c) 3,1,2,4","d":"(d)1,2,4,3","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Best method for preparing primary amines from alkyl halides  without changing the mumber of carbon atoms in the chain in","a":"(a) Hoffmann brotunde reaction","b":"(b) Gabriel phthalimide synthesis","c":"(c) Sandmeyer reaction","d":"(d) reaction with NH","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Propionamate on Hotfimum degradation gives","a":"(a) metylhylamine","b":"(b) ethyl amine","c":"(C) propylamine","d":"(d) ethyl cyanide","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Secondary amines could be prepared by  with","a":"(a) reduction of nitriles","b":"(b) Hofmann bromide action","c":"(c) reduction of amides","d":"(d) reduction of stres","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The total number of elections around the nitrogen atomin amines are","a":"(a) 8","b":"(b) 7","c":"(c)4","d":"(d) 3","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The number of primary amines of formda CH, Nis","a":"(a) 1","b":"(b) 3","c":"(c) 4","d":"(d) 2","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"The IUPAC name of diethyl isopropyl amine is","a":"(a)N-n ,Diethypropane 2 amine","b":"(b) N-N ,Diethypropane 1 amine","c":"(c) N-N-diethylpropylamine","d":"(d) N-N-diethylaminopropane","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Gabric's phthalimide symbeses is used in the preparation of","a":"(a) primary aromatic amines ","b":"(B) Secondary amines","c":"(c)Primary aliphatic amines","d":"(d) Tertiary amines","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"IUPAC name of product immed by action of methylamine with two moles of ethy","a":"(a) N,N-Dimethylathanenine","b":"(b) N,N-Diethylmethamine","c":"(c) N-Methyl ethanamin","d":"(d) N-Ehyl-N-methylethane","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The auction of sin compounds is most Preferrred the presence of","a":"(a)  PH/h2 in ethanol","b":"(b) sn+ hcl","c":"(c) PH, in ethanol","d":"(d) iron scrap and HCL","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"An alkyl or benzyl halide on reaction with an ethanolic 44 High basicity of Me-NH relative to Me,N in  solution of ammonia undergoes","a":"(a) electrophilic substitution reaction","b":"(b) nucleophilic substitution reaction","c":"(c) free radical mechanism","d":"(d) nucleophilic addition reaction","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"A primary amine is formal by an amide on treatment with  homine and alkali. The primary amine has","a":"(a) 1carbon atom less than amide","b":"(b) 1carbon atom more than mide","c":"(c) 1 hydrogen atom ass than amid","d":"(d) 1hydrogen atom more than amide","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Amines have","a":"(a) garlic odour","b":"(b) Fishy odour","c":"(c) Jasmine odour","d":"(d) bitter almonds Odour","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Aniline is less soluble in water than ethyl amine chap to","a":"(a) resonance stablization of benzene ring","b":"(b) resonance stabilization of Anilium ion","c":"(c) more hydrophobic nature of C6H5, group ThantC2H5 group","d":"(d) mere hydrophobic nature of C2H5, group than C6H5,","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Aliphatic amines are _basic thum NH, but aromatic amines  are _basic than NH","a":"(A) More, less","b":"(b) less, more","c":"(c) both (a) and b","d":"(d) None of these","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"The compound obtained by heating a mixture of a primary amine and chloroform with ethanolic potassium hydroxide (kOH) is","a":"(a) an alkyl cyanide","b":"b) a nitro compound","c":"(c) an alkyl isocyanide","d":"(d) an amide","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Hinsberg's method to separate amines is based on the","a":"(a) benzene sulphonyl chloride","b":"(b) benzene sulphonic acid","c":"(C) Ethyl Oxalate","d":"(d) acetyl chloride","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Which of the following statements is not correct regarding  aniline?","a":"(a) It is less basic than ethylamine","b":"(b) It can be stem-distilled","c":"(C) It Reacts With Sodium To Give Hydrogen","d":"(d) it is soluble in water","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"N-Ethylbenzene sulphonyl amide is strongly acidic and soluble in alkali due to presence of","a":"(a)strong electron donating sulphonyl group","b":"(b) strong electron withdrawing sulphonyl group","c":"(c) weak electron donating wulphonyl group","d":"(d) weak electron withdrawing sulphonyl group","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Arrange the following in increasing order of their ha  strength  vantine (1) p-nitroaniline (2) 2,4,6-trinaethylaniline  (3):3-methylaline (4)","a":"(a)1,3,2,4","b":"(b) 2,3,4,1","c":"(c) 3,1,2,4","d":"(d) 1,2,4,3","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Which of the slowing is a 3° amine?","a":"(a) 1-Medylcyclohexylamine","b":"(b) Triethylamine","c":"(c) tert- Butylamine","d":"(d) n- methylamine","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Which of the following agents would not be a good choice for reducing an aryl nitro compound to an amine","a":"(a) H2(excess)/Pt","b":"(b) LiAlH, in ether","c":"(c) Fe and HCI","d":"(d) Sand HCl","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The source of nitrogen in Gabriel synthesis of amines","a":"(a) sodiumide, NaN3","b":"(b) sodium nitrite, NaNO2","c":"(c) potassium cyanide, KCN","d":"(d)potassium phthalimide, C6H4(CO)2N^- K^+","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"The best Regeant converting 2-phenylpropanamede into  2-phenylpropanamine is...","a":"(a) excess H2","b":"(b) Br2 in aqueous NOH","c":"(C) Iodine In The Presence Of Red Phosphorus","d":"(d) LiALH2 in either","hint":"","correct":"d"},{"question":"Hoffmann bromamide degradation reaction is shown  by","a":"(a) aRNH2","b":"(b) ArCONH2","c":"ARNO2","d":"ARCH2NH2","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"Methylamine reacts with HNo2, to form...","a":"(a) CH2-O-N=o","b":"(b) C*H_{2} - O - C*H_{2}","c":"(c) cH2OH","d":"(d) CH2CHO","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Reduction of aromatic nitro compounds Using fe and hCL gives","a":"(a) aromatic oxime","b":"(b) aromatic hydrocarbon","c":"(c) aromatic primary amine","d":"(d) aromatic amide","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Acid anhydrides on reaction with primary amine gives","a":"(a) amide","b":"(b) imide","c":"(c) secondary amine","d":"(d) imine","hint":"","correct":"a"},{"question":"Best method for preparing primary amines from alkyl halideswithout changing the mumber of carbonatoms in the chain","a":"(a) Hoffman bromamide reaction","b":"(b) Gabriel phthalimide synthesis","c":"(c) Sandmeyers reaction","d":"(d) reaction With nH3","hint":"Gabriel phthalimide synthesis is the best method of preparing primary amines from alkyl halides without changing the number of carbon atoms in the chain","correct":"b"},{"question":"Ethanal on reaction with ammonia forms an imine (X) whichon reaction with nascent hydrogen gives (Y). Identify x and \"Y\".","a":"(a) Xis CH3CH=NH and Y is CH3NH2","b":"(b) Xis CH3CHOHNH2 and Y is CH3CH2NH2","c":"(c) Xis CH3CHOHNH2 and Y is CH3NH2","d":"(d) Xis CH3CH-NHand Y is CH3CH2NH2","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Acetaldehyde is reacted with ammonia followed byreduction in presence of hydrogen as a catalyst. The primaryamine so formed further reacts with acetaldehyde. TheSchiff's base formed during the reaction is:","a":"(a) CH3CH=NCH3","b":"(b) CH3CH=NCH2CH3","c":"(c) CH3 =NCH2CH3","d":"(d) CH3CH2CH=NCH3","hint":"","correct":"b"},{"question":"The reaction of ammonia and its derivatives wthaldehydes is called:","a":"(a) Nucleophilic substitution reaction","b":"(b) Electrophilic substitution reaction","c":"(c) Nucleophilic addition reaction","d":"(d) Electrophilic addition reaction","hint":"","correct":"c"},{"question":"Reductive alkylation of ammonia by means of an aldehydein presence of hydrogen as reducing agents results in  formation","a":"(a) Primary amines","b":"(b) Secondary amines","c":"(c) tertiary amines","d":"(d) mixture of three amines","hint":"Reductive alkylation of ammonia by means of  aldehyde in the presence of hydrogen as reducing agent will yield mixture of primary, secondary and ternary amines","correct":"d"}]